On the 25th of July 306 AD, Constantius I, ruler
of the western provinces of the Roman Empire,
died at York in northern England. The legions
there immediately proclaimed his son as the
new emperor, Constantine I. Little could
they have known that summer day in 306 AD
that the man to whom they had just sworn their
allegiance would change the course of history.
How did Constantine go from York in 306 AD to
converting the Roman Empire to Christianity
and building one of the greatest cities in the
world? This is the story of Constantine the Great,
the ruler who converted the Roman
Empire to Christianity.
The man known to history as Emperor Constantine
I or Constantine the Great is believed to have
been born on the 27th of February in the year
272 AD. While the day on which he was born,
the 27th of February, is known with near certainty
from ancient sources, there is more of a debate
about the year. He could have been born in
273 AD or 274 AD, although some historians
place his year of birth as late as 280 AD. The
strongest evidence supports the year 272 AD,
as several fourth-century writers claimed he was
65 years old when he died in May 337 AD. His full
Roman name was Flavius Constantinus, to which was
later added the name Valerius as well. Although
the year of his birth is disputed, there is
agreement that he was born in the city of Naissus
in the Roman province of Moesia Superior. This
is the modern-day city of Niš in Serbia.
Constantine’s father was Flavius Constantius,
a Roman military commander who was born in the
Balkans. around Moesia, where Serbia
and Kosovo lie today. He was, though,
said to be either an Illyrian or Thracian,
the tribal groups who in ancient times had
dominated the regions around modern-day Croatia,
Albania and Bulgaria. When Constantine was born,
Constantius was a young soldier. He would
rise to a position of major power within
the Roman Empire as Constantine was growing
up. Constantius entered into a relationship
with a Greek woman named Helena around 270 AD.
Constantine was their first and only child.
Helena came from a humble background. She was
an important figure in the history of the era,
for while Constantius was an adherent of the old
polytheistic religion of Rome and Greece, Helena
was a Christian. As such, she seemingly exposed
her son to the Christian faith at an early age.
It is unclear if Constantius and Helena were in a
legally binding union of any kind. He later left
her and married a woman named Theodora with whom
he had numerous further children.
Constantine’s life is unusually well documented
for a later Roman Emperor. While the emperors
of the first century AD were written about
extensively by ancient historians like Suetonius,
Tacitus and Cassius Dio, there are far fewer
biographies for later emperors. That changed
completely for Constantine. His role in
converting the Roman Empire to Christianity
meant that dozens of Christian historians in
the fourth and fifth centuries wrote about him.
Several of these accounts were written by
contemporaries of Constantine who lived
through the events of his reign. The most
notable is the Vita Constantini or Life of
Constantine written by Eusebius, the greatest
early historian of the Christian church. He
was born a few years before Constantine and died
two years after him, so their lives overlapped.
Subsequent Christian historians, such as
Sozomen added further details. Lactantius,
a slightly earlier Christian historian, knew
Constantine in the first half of his reign
and wrote a work entitled On the Deaths of
the Persecutors which shed a lot of light
on Constantine’s earlier years. However, while
Constantine’s life and reign are unusually well
documented, the nature of these sources creates
a problem in and of itself. They were nearly
all written by Christian scholars who wrote
about Constantine in hagiographical terms,
highlighting his successes in converting the
empire to Christianity. As such, they are
clearly biased accounts that exaggerated
Constantine’s accomplishments.
When Constantine was born in the early 270s AD the
Roman Empire had been in the midst of a crisis for
nearly forty years. The Severan Dynasty which
had ruled the empire between 193 AD and 235 AD
had been succeeded by decades of civil war. There
were dozens of emperors between 235 AD and 284 AD.
On top of this, the northern and eastern borders
of the empire were assailed by a combination of
Germanic tribes. These included the Franks and
Sarmatians in Europe and the Sassanid Persians and
Palmyrans in the Middle East. Alongside these
assaults from outsiders, hyperinflation and
pandemics impacted on the empire economically and
socially. The Third Century Crisis only came to
an end in 284 AD when the Emperor Diocletian rose
to the throne. Constantine’s father had decided
to support Diocletian’s claim to the throne. As
a result, Constantius benefited accordingly after
Diocletian’s 21-year long reign began. In 293 AD,
in order to ensure a peaceful transfer of power in
the future, Diocletian established a college of
emperors known as the Tetrarchy. This structure
outlined a new format for Roman rule. There would
be two senior emperors, known as the augusti,
and two junior emperors, known as the caesares.
He appointed Constantius as one of the caesares.
As such, while Constantine was growing up, his
father’s support for Diocletian promoted the
family to become part of the ruling elite. If
all went well, the idea was that Constantius
would subsequently succeed to become one
of the more senior augusti. Accordingly,
this could open a place for Constantine to
enter the Tetrarchy at that point.
These shifting political events meant that
Constantine did not spend much time around
his father when he was young. When he was an
infant, for instance, Constantius was serving
as a commander of the personal guard of Aurelian,
the Emperor between 270 AD and 275 AD. He moved
around constantly in the years that followed and
it is likely that Constantine was primarily raised
by his mother, Helena. Eusebius stated in his
Life of Constantine that the future emperor had
“reaped the advantages of a liberal education.”
This involved learning subjects like history,
philosophy and rhetoric that the Romans prized
greatly. He was taught in Latin and this became
his primary language despite his mother’s
Greek heritage. Later in life Constantine
required translators to aid him in some official
duties in the Greek-speaking east. Constantine’s
teenage years were spent at Diocletian’s court
in the city of Nicomedia, modern-day Ízmit in
western Turkey. Historians remain divided on
how directly exposed he was to Christianity
here during his youth. For instance, one of the
learned preachers in Nicomedia during this time
of Constantine’s childhood was the Christian
scholar Lactantius. As we have seen, Lactantius
later became a key source on events in the Roman
Empire during Constantine’s rise to power.
Diocletian was certainly not a supporter of
Christians of any kind. Christianity had grown
massively in the third century to become
part of the politics of the Roman Empire.
The new religion had started out as a radical
sect of Judaism in the Levant in the middle
of the first century AD. It spread thereafter
through the Greek-speaking Eastern Mediterranean,
yet it remained a minor faith with small, isolated
communities of Christians in places like Antioch,
Corinth, Alexandria and the coastal cities of
what is now Turkey. It continued to grow slowly,
albeit steadily in the second century AD. From
the 160s AD onwards there were a growing number
of Pagan Greco-Roman writers in the Eastern
Mediterranean, pointing out that the values
of the Christians fundamentally conflicted with
those of mainstream Roman society. Nevertheless,
despite the claims made by later Christian
writers, there was no sustained policy of
persecuting Christians in the Roman Empire until
the reign of the Emperor Decius between 249 AD
and 251 AD. The shift in attitude was occasioned
by the massive growth of the Christian movement
in the third century. Historians, theologians and
even sociologists still debate why this occurred.
The most likely explanation is that the Third
Century Crisis created such a volatile political
and social environment across the Roman Empire
that this radical religion, with its emphasis on
salvation in the afterlife, became attractive to
a growing number of people. Even Decius’ campaign
of persecution was brief. Instead, the most
substantial attack on the Christians came during
the later years of the reign of Diocletian, by
which time there were several million Christians
across the empire. In 303 AD he launched the Great
Persecution. In this the rights of Christians
across the empire were restricted and they were
ordered to make the standard sacrifices to the
emperor on pain of punishment. As a member of the
Tetrarchy, Constantine’s father was responsible
for overseeing the Great Persecution in some
of the western provinces of the empire.
Could you use “DESS-eee-us here
Diocletian’s initiation of the Great Persecution
was one of the last major acts of his eventful
reign. Two years later, on the 1st of May 305 AD,
he made the unusual decision to retire and
hand over the office of augustus. This was
all seemingly in the interest of ensuring
that the Tetrarchy system functioned as it
was supposed to and there was a smooth transfer
of power. In the western provinces, Constantius
was elevated to become one of the augusti. In the
east, Constantine had hoped that when Diocletian
stepped down that he might be appointed as one of
the caesares, the junior emperors in the Tetrarchy
system. However, this did not happen. Instead,
the new senior emperor in the east, Galerius,
appointed his nephew, Maximinus Daza, as the
new caesar in the east. Fearing that he might
now be killed by Galerius, who was effectively
holding him hostage at his court, Constantine
fled westwards and joined his father in Gaul near
modern-day Boulogne in northern France. When he
reached Gaul, his father was preparing to lead
an army over the English Channel to campaign in
Britain. This was against the Picts of Caledonia
who were pressing south from what is now Scotland
into northern England. Constantius was seemingly
already ill and he died at Eboracum, the name of
the Roman city of York, on the 25th of July 306
AD. The legions there immediately proclaimed his
son as his successor, a move which was a breach
of the Tetrarchy system, as Constantine had never
been established as one of the caesares. Hence,
civil war beckoned yet again within months of
Diocletian’s abdication. For his part, Constantine
later made it part of his official propaganda that
he had not requested the legions to proclaim him
as emperor at York. Constantine argued that they
had done so anyway, in the process creating the
notion that he was a figure of such popularity
that he had had the imperial title thrust upon
him. The Civil Wars of the Tetrarchy that now
began in 306 AD, and which would last down to
324 AD, would change the course of history.
MAX-imin-us
If the Tetrarchy system
had functioned in the way that it was supposed
to, a commander named Severus, who had become
the caesar in the western provinces in 305 AD
when Constantius became one of the augusti,
should have become the undisputed augusti in the
west when Constantius died. Constantine could
then have been promoted to become the new caesar
if Severus had agreed that he should enter the
imperial college. Instead, though, Constantine
claimed his father’s senior position, opening
up a civil war between himself and Severus. The
picture was further complicated by Maxentius. He
was a son of Maximian, who had ruled alongside
Diocletian down to 305 AD. Like Constantine,
Maxentius had been passed over for earlier
promotion. In October 306 AD, when news arrived
to Italy where Maxentius was based at the time of
Constantius’ death, the legions under his control
proclaimed him as the new emperor. Severus was
not far away in Milan and headed south to confront
Maxentius. He was defeated, captured and died
not long afterwards in 307 AD. This meant that
the struggle for power in the west of the empire
was now broadly between Constantine and Maxentius.
While Maxentius had control over Italy and
secured the provinces of North Africa, Constantine
secured control over Gaul and Hispania.
Constantine and Maxentius had something in common;
neither of them were able to gain acceptance as
a legitimate ruler in the west from the senior
augustus in the east, Emperor Galerius. Instead,
at an imperial conference held at Carnuntum on the
11th of November 308 AD in what is now Austria,
it was decided that Licinius, an ally of Galerius,
would become the new augustus of the western
half of the empire. The conference at Carnuntum
was given added gravitas by the presence of the
retired Emperor Diocletian. Although an effort
was made to conciliate Constantine by making
him caesar in the west, he was unsatisfied with
this. Instead he briefly drew closer to Maxentius.
Constantine had entered into a marriage alliance
with his rival in the west the previous year by
marrying Maxentius’ sister, Fausta. Their father,
Maximian, who had abdicated his position as
augustus in 305 AD at the same time as Diocletian,
but who had re-entered the political fray in 306
AD, was also involved in these complex political
manoeuvres. Fausta was probably Constantine’s
second wife. Years earlier he had entered
into a relationship with a woman named Minervina
while he was residing at the court of Diocletian.
They had a son together named Crispus. It is
unclear if Minervina was Constantine’s wife
or a concubine. In any event, he put her aside
in 307 AD in order to marry Fausta and form an
alliance with Maxentius. Constantine and Fausta
would remain married for many years and they
had five children together, three sons and two
daughters, Constantina, Constantine, Constantius,
Constans and Helena. However, the alliance
between Maxentius and Constantine disintegrated
long before most of these children were born. In
310 AD, Maxentius and Fausta’s father, Maximian,
tried to overthrow Constantine in Gaul. He was
defeated, and his actions led to a spiral of
events which led to Constantine and Maxentius
entering into direct war with one another for
control over the western provinces. By then
Maxentius had become extremely unpopular and was
facing local rebellions in Italy. And so it was
that Constantine campaigned towards Rome in 312
AD. The resulting clash between his and Maxentius’
forces at the Milvian Bridge outside Rome on the
28th of October 312 AD has become one of the
most famous military clashes in history.
On the surface, the story of the Battle
of the Milvian Bridge was quite routine.
Two rival claimants for the Roman imperial
title clashed in battle. Constantine’s forces
won the battle after Maxentius drowned in
the River Tiber, and Constantine became
the unrivalled ruler of the western provinces.
However, the significance of the Battle of the
Milvian Bridge lies in Constantine’s alleged
conversion to Christianity as a result of
the battle. There are actually two completely
different versions of what happened. Lactantius
claimed in On the Deaths of the Persecutors
that Constantine had a dream vision the night
before the battle in which he was instructed to
have his men adorn their shields with a Chi-Rho,
an early Christian symbol of Christ. As a
result of doing so, his men won the battle and
Constantine was inspired thereafter to become a
Christian ruler. The other version of the story of
Constantine’s conversion was related by Eusebius.
He claimed that during the battle Constantine and
his soldiers saw a shining Christian cross in the
sky. Constantine interpreted this as a divine sign
of the providence of the Christian god. Eusebius’
version became more popular over time with its
epic appearance of a shining cross in the sky
as the battle raged around the emperor.
KAI-ROW
Constantine claimed that he was inspired enough
by his vision at the Battle of the Milvian Bridge
that he proceeded in the immediate aftermath of
it to end the persecution of the Christians. In
February 313 AD, the Edict of Milan was issued to
that effect. Here it was proclaimed that “we have
given to those Christians free and unrestricted
opportunity of religious worship.” Several things
are usually overlooked with the Edict of Milan
however. Firstly, the Edict went on to declare
that “we have also conceded to other religions the
right of open and free observance of their worship
for the sake of the peace of our times.” Secondly,
the preamble of the Edict states very clearly
that it was being issued after Constantine had
met with his major remaining rival for power. This
was the ruler of the eastern provinces, Licinius,
and at Milan both had agreed on the measure
together. Thus, the Edict of Milan was not
a declaration by Constantine that Christianity
was to be tolerated henceforth. It was a joint
declaration by Constantine and Licinius that all
religions were to be tolerated across the empire
in order to end religious tensions among the
Roman people. The question of what motivated
Constantine has absorbed the attention of
historians for centuries. In all likelihood,
he and Licinius had decided that it was pointless
to try to curb the seemingly unstoppable rise
of Christianity. They decided to tolerate the
Christians as a means of stabilising the empire
after the crises of the third century. Indeed,
one of the last acts of Galerius, the senior
emperor in the east, prior to his death in 311
AD, had been to issue the Edict of Serdica. This
proclamation ended Diocletian’s Great Persecution
in the eastern provinces and established the same
idea of tolerance that Constantine and Licinius
guaranteed at Milan two years later.
The popular view is that Constantine firmly
committed to Christianity owing to his experiences
at the Battle of the Milvian Bridge. According to
this version of events, by the later stages of his
reign the Roman Empire had become a Christian
state and steps were already being taken to
eradicate Pagan superstition. That
at least is the myth of Constantine,
who is venerated as a Christian saint. The
only problem is this is not what happened at
all. While Constantine did end the persecution
of the Christians through the Edict of Milan and
would move to establish a Christian church
throughout the empire as his reign went on,
he continued to worship the old gods and did not
view Christianity as being an exclusive religion.
For instance, long after the Milvian Bridge, coins
were issued with Constantine’s image on one side
and images of Jupiter, the old Roman king of
the gods on the other. He also connected his
reign to Sol Invictus, a Sun deity that had become
extremely popular in the third century AD. There
is evidence to indicate that Constantine viewed
the Christian god as being a Sun deity as well.
Overall, his religious outlook was one
in which he viewed Christianity as a
new component of the broad tapestry of
religious life across the empire. He did
not reject the older religion or other cults
like that of Sol Invictus.
The meeting between Constantine and Licinius
at Milan in 313 AD was important for multiple
reasons. The Edict was issued there and a marriage
alliance was also entered into as Licinius
married Constantine’s half-sister, Flavia Julia
Constantia. The alliance was a temporary one,
but Licinius needed it to secure his power. He
faced a rival claimant for power in the east,
Maximinus Daza, the nephew of Galerius
who had been made a caesar back in 305 AD.
Indeed, Licinius might well have been the
driving force behind the Edict of Milan to
a greater extent than we realise. Maximinus Daza
was a persecutor of the Christians in the lands
he controlled in Egypt and the Levant, which were
provinces where Christianity had flourished since
the second century AD. Licinius may have been
trying to undermine Daza’s position by appealing
to the Christians of those lands. Shortly after
the meeting at Milan, Licinius defeated Daza at
the Battle of Tzirallum on the 30th of April 313
AD. He was killed soon after and Constantine and
Licinius briefly ruled the western and eastern
halves of the empire in relative peace. Renewed
conflict broke out between them, though, in
316 AD. Constantine won an initial victory at
the Battle of Mardis that winter, but the tensions
between them continued to simmer and they returned
to war at the start of the 320s AD. Constantine’s
twin victories at sea and on land, at the Battles
of the Hellespont and Chrysopolis respectively,
in the summer and autumn of 324 AD brought these
civil wars to an end. This saw a conclusion to
the conflict that had followed the abdication of
Diocletian and left Constantine as the sole ruler
of the Roman Empire, seventeen and a half years
after he was first proclaimed as emperor.
MAX-imin-us
One of Constantine’s first acts as ruler of
a consolidated Roman Empire was to initiate
plans for a new capital. Nova Roma or
‘New Rome’, as it was initially named,
was to be located where Europe met Asia. The new
capital would be strategically located to allow
an emperor residing there to respond to attacks
against both the northern and eastern borders.
The location that he chose was on the European
side of the Bosporus, the waterway separating
the Balkans from Turkey and the Mediterranean
Sea from the Black Sea. The symbolic foundation
of the city of Constantinople, as it eventually
became known, here on the 24th of November 326
AD was not a revolutionary break with the past.
There had been a settlement at this location,
known as Byzantium, going back centuries to
when the Greeks had colonised this part of
the world. Furthermore, Diocletian had recognised
the need for a capital in this part of the empire
to respond to issues as they arose in the east.
He had therefore kept his court at Nicomedia,
where Constantine had spent a large
part of his youth and early adult years.
Constantinople was closely modelled after Rome in
many ways. For instance, a claim was made that the
new capital was being built on seven hills, like
Rome had been, while the city centre was laid
out to mimic Rome. What made Constantinople as
distinctive was its Christian character. Christian
churches were located prominently here, albeit
the grand church of Hagia Sophia was not built
until much later.
Eusebius’ extremely extensive Life of Constantine
contains limited details on the emperor’s early
life. Conversely, it is immensely detailed about
Constantine’s actions after he secured full
control of the empire in 324 AD. It is also highly
informative about the reforms that he initiated
to establish a hierarchical Christian Church
that was interconnected with the Roman state.
Constantine did so at an unprecedented ecumenical
council which he convened at the city of Nicaea
on the Turkish side of the Bosporus in the summer
of 325 AD. This was presided over by Constantine
and attended by around 250 bishops drawn from
across the empire, and even from the lands of
the Scythians and Persians beyond Rome’s borders.
The Council of Nicaea was a defining event in the
early history of Christianity. The Council saw
the Christian church organised more effectively
and adjudication over a number of theological
disputes. These included the dating of Easter,
the establishment of what became known
as the Nicene Creed as a statement of
Christian faith and, most importantly of all, the
deliberations on the nature of the Holy Trinity.
The issue of the Trinity had become controversial
owing to the teachings of a North African bishop
named Arius who claimed that Jesus was not
co-eternal with God, but was instead a more
junior celestial that had been created by
God. Throughout his Life, Eusebius tried to
make clear that Constantine aimed for a church
that was unified politically and theologically.
He stated that Constantine uttered the following
in his address to the assembled bishops: “I feel
that my desires will be most completely fulfilled
when I can see you all united in one judgment,
and that common spirit of peace and concord
prevailing among you all.” On the disunity of
the Christian community, Constantine commented
specifically: “Begin from this moment to discard
the causes of that disunion which has existed
among you, and remove the perplexities of
controversy by embracing the principles of peace.”
Yet what Eusebius depicted as an emperor bent on
establishing peace, could just as easily be
interpreted as a power grab. Constantine,
the dual Pagan-Christian ruler, wanted a
unified church without divisions. Such a Church,
unified and bound to the state, would be much
easier for him to dominate as Emperor.
While the nature of Constantine’s Christianity is
clearly open to debate, there is no denying that
his actions were incredibly successful. Estimates
are that there were perhaps only around a quarter
of a million Christians throughout the Roman
Empire in 200 AD, out of a total population of as
many as 50 or 60 million people. Undoubtedly that
number had increased to a few million Christians
by the time Constantine was proclaimed as emperor
in York in 306 AD. But Christians were still very
much in the minority across the empire. That all
changed because of Constantine’s reign. He was
not unique in deciding to tolerate Christianity
at the start of the 310s AD. Both Licinius and
Galerius had decided on the same course of
action. He was also a peculiar Christian,
one who was able to integrate worship of the
Christian god into his own polytheism that
included strong veneration of the Sun deity, Sol
Invictus. However, he laid the groundwork for the
establishment of a strong Christian church and
his reign was long enough that, by the end of it,
the triumph of Christianity as a state religion
was assured to a large extent. In the decades that
followed, millions of people began converting
to Christianity across the empire.
Constantine’s reign is understandably the focus
for the creation of the Christian church and
the building of Constantinople. However, there
were numerous other issues which Constantine was
concerned with. The fiscal crisis that had gripped
the empire in the third century had not gone away.
While the Romans were brilliant engineers and
administrators, they had a limited grasp of
economics. The crisis of the third century
had forced them to consider monetary policy.
Diocletian had issued an Edict on Maximum Prices
in 301 AD to try to curb inflation, setting upper
limits to both prices and wages. Numerous emperors
had tried other methods, engaging in recoinage
whereby new coins were issued with higher silver
and gold purity to create fresh confidence in the
coins that were circulating. Diocletian also tried
this, issuing a new silver coin that was said to
be pure silver. However, it wasn’t long before
versions of the coin began to circulate where the
silver was mixed with other metals. Constantine’s
innovation was that that he began issuing ‘billon’
coins that were a mix of silver and alloy metals.
He did mint and distribute a new gold coin as a
kind of premier piece of coinage, but in issuing
the ‘billon’ he was getting rid of the pretence
that the silver coins in circulation were pure.
He also ordered the melting down of statues made
of gold, silver and bronze from Pagan temples
and used the metal to have new coins minted.
Christian writers subsequently cheered
on this activity, interpreting it as a
sign of Constantine’s animosity towards
the old Pagan religion. In reality it
could be interpreted as a practical measure,
allowing the state to acquire precious metals,
rather than any indication of his antagonism
towards the old polytheistic religious cults.
Constantine’s reign, like that of any Roman
emperor, witnessed the construction of monuments
and statues. What marked Constantine’s time
in power as distinct was that his reign lasted
over three decades, so he simply built more than
others. What is unusual is that, despite creating
his own capital city at Constantinople, the two
pieces of art and architecture which Constantine
is most famous for were both constructed in old
Rome in Italy, not the New Rome on the Bosporus.
These are the Arch of Constantine and the Colossus
of Constantine. The Arch of Constantine lies
between the Colosseum and the Palatine Hill in
Rome and is still standing to this day. It is
a classic Roman commemorative arch, celebrating
Constantine’s victory over Maxentius at the Battle
of the Milvian Bridge. What is remarkable about
the Arch of Constantine is its sheer size. It is
the largest triumphal arch in the city, standing
21 metres tall. By comparison, the Arch of Titus,
built to commemorate Roman victory in the
First Roman-Jewish War between 66 AD and 73 AD,
is 15 metres tall. This being said, Constantine
was magpie-like in the methods he allowed his
architects to employ. Many of the reliefs
decorating the outside of his arch were
literally ripped out of the triumphal arches of
other emperors and recycled for his monument.
The Colossus of Constantine was erected
in the Basilica of Maxentius in the Roman
Forum. It would have stood 15 metres high
when first built in ancient times. However,
it was destroyed in its original format in ancient
times and was possibly broken up for looting when
the Goths sacked the city in 410 AD. The head,
which alone is two and a half metres tall,
has survived, along with some other fragments. A
full replica of the enormous statue was installed
in the Capitoline Museum in Rome in 2024.
Constantine’s later reign was not entirely
devoid of controversy. In the summer of 326 AD, as
work accelerated to establish the New Rome on the
Bosporus, Constantine appears to have ordered
the killing of both his wife, Fausta, and his
eldest child, Crispus, the son from his earlier
relationship with Minervina. His motives for doing
so are not entirely clear. Eusebius conveniently
avoided mentioning the pair and their murders.
The general consensus amongst later writers
was that Crispus was killed first and then
Fausta was murdered a few weeks later in a
bathhouse. Zosimus, a historian writing at
the very end of the fifth century AD stated that
Constantine acted when he learned that the pair
had become engaged in a sexual relationship with
each other. He stated that Constantine “killed
Crispus … when he incurred suspicion of him having
sexual relations with his stepmother Fausta,
without taking any notice of the laws of nature.”
Zosimus expands on the story to account for the
pair’s death in detail, writing that “Constantine
then tried to remedy the evil with a greater evil:
having ordered baths to be heated above the normal
level, he deposited Fausta in them and brought
her out when she was dead.” An alternate theory is
that Constantine was trying to stamp his authority
over the imperial family. He had witnessed
Maxentius overpower his own father, Maximian,
in the western provinces nearly two decades
earlier. As a result, Constantine may have been
concerned that something similar could happen as
his sons grew up and their mother schemed on their
behalf. Thus, the murders of Fausta and Crispus
may have been a strategic initiative to indicate
that Constantine would not tolerate any effort
to dilute his power as he grew older.
Constantine certainly did not betray any signs
that he was aging poorly through his fifties and
into his sixties. He continued to campaign
militarily throughout the remainder of his
reign. The empire was more secure in the early
fourth century AD than it had been half a century
earlier when the Franks, Alemanni and Sarmatians
had penetrated deep into Gaul and the Balkans.
However, even at this later point in Constantine’s
lifetime, the borders were still in a precarious
state. Constantine had been able to secure
the frontier in Germania early on in his reign
through the location of his capital being
established at Trier, near the River Rhine,
in the years prior to the Battle of the Milvian
Bridge. During these years, while an unstable
peace existed between him, Maxentius and Maximian
in the west, Constantine had campaigned against
various Germanic tribes such as the Bructeri, as
well as the Franks and Alemanni. Constantine also
left behind reinforced border defences
along the Rhine when he went eastwards
to confront Licinius.
Thereafter, Constantine’s focus when it came
to Rome’s borders was in campaigning against the
Sarmatians and other groups in the Balkans. These
tribes had been in control of large parts of Dacia
in modern-day Romania for half a century. This had
come after the Emperor Aurelian had strategically
withdrawn from the lands north of the River Danube
back when Constantine was an infant. With the
border along the Rhine reinforced, the empire
secure internally, and the Romans enjoying an
extended period of peace with Persia in the east,
Constantine developed his ambition to try to
reconquer Dacia. Crispus campaigned against
the Alemanni and secured the gap between the Rhine
and Danube Rivers in the mid-320s. Perhaps it was
this military success which cost Crispus his life
not long afterwards, as his father became wary of
his ambitions. Thereafter, with the western flank
secure, Constantine campaigned into Dacia. Between
328 AD and 332 AD he was active almost every
year along the frontier in what we now call
Serbia and Romania. Here, Constantine won several
victories, establishing a series of new defensive
structures, although his claims that he fully
reconquered Dacia were exaggerated.
Constantine was active until late in his life.
He was preparing a large offensive against the
Persians in 336 AD and was said to have developed
a plan to be baptised like Jesus in the waters of
the River Jordan on his way through the Levant.
However, the plan was never implemented. In the
late winter or early spring of 337 AD, Constantine
became ill. He never fully recovered. Instead,
he withdrew to Nicomedia, where he had spent so
much of his life in his youth and early adult
years. There, the man who had begun converting the
Roman Empire to Christianity, was finally baptised
on his deathbed. Strangely, the cleric who carried
out the ceremony was Eusebius of Nicomedia, not to
be confused with his biographer of the same name.
This other Eusebius was an adherent of the Arian
heresy that the Council of Nicaea had tried to
eradicate. Not long afterwards, Constantine died
on the 22nd of May 337 AD. He was probably around
65 years of age, though we cannot be sure. He was
laid to rest in a sarcophagus in the Church of
the Holy Apostles in Constantinople. His remains
were destroyed at some stage in the thirteenth
century during the chaos that had enveloped the
city following its conquest by the Christians
of the Fourth Crusade.
Constantine was succeeded upon his death by three
of his sons, Constantine II, Constantius II and
Constans I. However, while the Constantinian
Dynasty managed to hang on to imperial power,
there was internal conflict. The brothers
quickly became rivals. Constantine II was killed
while campaigning into Italy. Constantius II and
Constans I then ruled together down to 350 AD when
Constans was usurped and killed in the western
provinces by a rebel general named Magnentius.
Constantius was the longest-lived of these sons
of Constantine the Great. When he died in 361 AD,
he was succeeded by his first cousin, Constantine
the Great’s nephew, Julian. This young emperor was
clearly a man of ability, though he broke
completely with the religious tradition
established by his uncle. In direct contrast to
Constantine’s apparent embrace of Christianity,
Julian began trying to convert the empire back
to Paganism and re-orientate it towards Hellenic
philosophy. Julian could well have changed the
history of the ancient world if he had ruled
for three decades like his uncle and been able
pursue his goals for more than 30 years. However,
he died less than two years after he assumed the
imperial purple while campaigning against the
Persians in the east. His premature passing in the
summer of 363 AD brought the Constantinian Dynasty
to an end. Thereafter the empire reverted to a
less linear form of succession. All of Julian’s
successors were Christians. Many of them, like
the Emperor Theodosius, introduced laws which
specifically aimed to persecute non-Christians
in ways that would have been unthinkable in
Constantine’s time. The shift towards Christianity
becoming a religion of persecution thus happened
in the second half of the fourth century,
not during the reign of Constantine.
Constantine I was probably the second most
important ruler of the Roman Empire in the
500 years between the establishment of
the imperial system in 27 BC and the fall
of the Western Roman Empire in 476 AD. His
importance within the history of the Roman
Empire was eclipsed only by Caesar Augustus, the
man who created the empire and returned the Roman
world to stability after decades of civil war and
anarchy. Constantine’s reign was also the third
longest in that time period. His ascent was both
unexpected and typical of the time he lived in.
On the one hand, a stable system of
succession via a college of emperors
had been set up by Diocletian when Constantine
was a young man. If this had operated properly,
Constantine would not have become
the ruler of the empire. Conversely,
if looked at from the perspective of the wider
third century in which Constantine was born, his
rise to power via civil wars and rivalries with
other would-be emperors was completely normal.
What was altogether different about Constantine
was what he did when he became emperor. After
securing control over the western half of the
empire, he issued an official edict of toleration
for Christian worship which was followed by
the organisation of the Christian Church into
a mass political institution. After becoming the
undisputed ruler of the entire empire in 324 AD,
he then built a great new capital in the east. The
conversion of the Roman Empire to Christianity,
and the construction of what would become one of
the greatest cities of the world throughout the
medieval era and down to the present day, are the
two great achievements of Constantine’s reign.
And yet, there
is still no certainty today, 1700 years later,
as to what Constantine’s real religious beliefs
were. It remains a matter of debate as to whether
the conversion of the empire was facilitated by
Constantine’s personal beliefs, or whether it came
from his tactical political manoeuvre to increase
imperial stability through greater tolerance of
rival religions. In the end, his motives really
do not matter. Constantine stands at the very
centre of a religious and political revolution
in the Late Roman Empire which changed the history
of the world. For that reason, he surely deserves
to be called Constantine the Great.
What do you think of Constantine the Great?
Was he a genuine Christian believer? Or was he
an opportunist who saw the Christian Church as
something which he could utilise to cement
his control over the Roman Empire? Please
let us know in the comment section, and in the
meantime, thank you very much for watching.